Pittsfield, Mass. First Church of Christ records, 1764-1864.
Congregational Library & Archives
Pittsfield, Mass. First Church of Christ records, 1764-1864.
RG5411
Congregational Library & Archives
0.66 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
The First Church of Christ in Pittsfield, Massachusetts, was first organized in February 1764. Thomas Allen was called to be the first minister of the church and he was ordained as pastor on April 18, 1764. Construction on the first meeting house was completed in 1770 and construction on the second meeting house was completed in 1793. Thomas Allen's political beliefs resulted in a schism in 1809 which resulted in the formation of the Second Union Church. The churches reunited in 1818 under the pastorate of Dr. Heman Humphrey. In 1846, black members of the church withdrew to form the Second Congregational Church and in 1850 another group of members withdrew to form the South Congregational Church. The second meeting house was partially destroyed in 1851 and construction was completed on the third meeting house in 1853. In 1952, the church underwent a major renovation. The First Church of Christ continues to serve the Pittsfield community today. This collection contains administrative and vital records for the church and includes vital member records as well as church meeting minutes and ministerial records. The collection also contains ministerial records relating to the last decades of Thomas Allen's pastorate, including records related to the political schism of the church.
Allen, Thomas, 1743-1810
First Church of Christ (Pittsfield, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were temporarily deposited for digitization to the Congregational Library & Archives by First Church of Christ in Pittsfield, Massachusetts, in March, 2020; 2020-05.
Location of Originals
Materials in this collection are held and maintained by the Berkshire Athenaeum in Pittsfield, Massachusetts.
Digital Copies
Records within this collection were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions may be accessed online through our digital archive.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The First Church of Christ in Pittsfield, Massachusetts, was first organized in February 1764. Construction on the first meeting house was begun in 1761 but work was not completed until 1770. Thomas Allen was called to be the first minister of the church and he was ordained as pastor on April 18, 1764. Planning for a second meeting house began in 1789 in order to meet the needs of the growing congregation and construction was completed in 1793.
Thomas "Parson" Allen was also called the "Fighting Parson" and was well remembered for his strong support for the American Revolution. He was said to carry his musket into his pulpit and was supposed to have fired the first shot against the British at the Battle of Bennington. Thomas Allen also had strongly held political beliefs. During the American Revolution, Allen was very anti-loyalist and following the American Revolution Allen's political beliefs became anti-federalist. This led to a schism within his church along political lines during the last years of his ministry; Allen even offered to resign in 1809 over the schism though ultimately poor health and eventually his death in 1810 meant that his resignation was never accepted. From this schism the Second Union Church of Pittsfield was formed by Federalists in 1809.
Thomas Allen's son, William Allen took over the pastorate of the First Church of Christ following his father's death. By 1816, there was talk of reuniting the First Church of Christ and the Second Union Church and in 1818 both were reunited under the pastorate of Dr. Heman Humphrey. Under Humphrey the Pittsfield Sabbath School Association was formed which included Congregationalists, Methodists, and Baptists. Humphrey resigned from the pastorate in 1823 to become the president of Amherst College. In 1846, black members of the First Church of Christ withdrew to form the Second Congregational Church. In 1850 another group of members withdrew to form the South Congregational Church.
During the ministry of John Todd, on February 9, 1851, the second meeting house was partially destroyed by a fire. Construction on the third meeting house, which was designed to be a stone building, began in May 1852 and was completed on July 1853. A parish house and chapel was added to the building between 1868 and 1870. This was renovated and expanded in 1893. In 1899, the French Church in Pittsfield was established with members meeting at the third meeting house and the Italian Church was likewise established not long after in 1908. The First Church of Christ became the first Congregational church in the United States, in 1907, to join the home missions movement on its own by sponsoring T. S. Whitey and his work in Wyoming. In 1952, the whole church was renovated; that same year the church and parish were incorporated as a single entity. Three years later, in 1955, the French and Italian churches formally merged with the First Church of Christ.
The First Church of Christ in Pittsfield continues to serve the community to this day.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains administrative and vital records for the First Church of Christ in Pittsfield, Massachusetts. These records include church meeting minutes, membership records, ministerial records, baptismal records, marriage records, and records of death. The collection also contains ministerial records related to the later years of Thomas Allen's pastorate. Included in those ministerial records are records related to a schism which formed in the church along political lines due to Allen's political beliefs.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in chronological order by start date.
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Bibliography
A Brief History of the First Church of Christ in Pittsfield, Congregational. 17.11.1 P68.7 FrCC
Plunkett, H. M. The Old Pittsfield Church and Its Three Meeting-Houses. Boston: New England Magazine, 1893. 17.11.1 P68.7 FrCC
Baptismal records.; Church controversies.; Church discipline.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Clergy -- Finance, Personal.; Clergy -- Salaries, etc.; Covenants (Church polity).; Creeds.; Funeral sermons.; Installation (clergy).; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Allen, Thomas, 1743-1810; First Church of Christ (Pittsfield, Mass.)
- Church records, 1764 1817; 1764-1817
  Scope and Contents
  This volume of church records contains both the administrative records of the church and vital records for church members and Pittsfield inhabitants. The volume contains copies of the church's covenant and confession of faith, church meeting minutes, records of votes, and records relating to church disciplinary cases, including a list of confessions given to the church. The vital records within the volume also contain membership records, baptismal records, marriage records, and records of deaths.
- Deeds, 1772 1807; 1772-1807
- Thomas Allen shorthand manuscripts, 1781 1803; 1781-1803
- Thomas Allen papers, 1783 1808; 1783-1808
- Thomas Allen sermons and remarks, 1783, undated
- Thomas Allen financial records, 1795 1806; circa 1795-1806
- Thomas Allen papers, 1798 1805; 1798-1805, undated
- Thomas Allen funeral sermon, 1799 1961; 1799, 1961
- Thomas Allen schism records, 1805 1809; circa 1805-1809
- Thomas Allen schism records, 1807 1809; circa 1807-1809
- Thomas Allen schism records, 1807 1809; circa 1807-1809
- Thomas Allen resignation, 1809
- Church records, 1817 1864; 1817-1864
  This volume of church records contains both the administrative records and vital records of the church. The vital records include lists of baptisms, marriage, deaths, and membership records. The administrative records include church meeting minutes, extensive records of votes, a copy of the church covenant, and records relation to the installation of ministers.
- Church register, 1824 1842; 1824-1842
  This church registry contains vital records for the church as well as some ministerial records. The records within the volume begin after the installation of Rufus W. Bailey and continue through the pastorates of Henry Philip Tappan, John W. Yeomans, Horatio Nelson Brinsmade, and ends with the installation of John Todd. The register includes records of admissions and dismissions, baptismal records, marriage records, records of deaths, and copies of some ministerial correspondence, as well as copies of standard form letters.
- Rome manuscript, undated